junkyard love podcast at what age do we
learn how to have better
convers a real junkard love podcast it's
kind of a dichotomy I ended
up in Nebraska that's where I'm from
trying to get out of Nebraska by joining
the Navy and I joined the Navy to be a
radar air traffic control specialist and
through a mistaken orders I ended up at
the uh SEAL training center in Coronado
after I completed Air Traffic Control
radar school and when I got there they
talked me into volunteering for the Seal
program so I that's pretty much my life
in a nutshell the every time I kind of
think I've got a a strategic plan or an
idea you know gained out some
opportunity a window opens up and I W
say it's a gut instinct but sometimes I
can just see it for what it is
especially if you're looking for it
which is something I I talk about a lot
in my books and my speeches if you're
open to it it's kind of like punch buggy
soon as somebody plays punch bug you
suddenly see vots wagon beels everywhere
right but up until that point you didn't
see any because you weren't thinking
about it you weren't aware of it so
that's the same thing with opportunity
so my life is more of a zigzag of
jumping through Windows of opportunity
um I you know I was in listed the seal
for 10 years then I decided to become an
officer so I was an officer for 10 years
in seals and then I went to manage money
as you noted in the intro and then 9111
happened and then I got pulled out of
the money management thing after eight
years into counterterrorism using some
of my old skills the US
government uh and then I ended up in a
Government Contracting large Government
Contracting Company and started doing um
basically business management of
operations but then I got pulled because
I was pretty successful at marketing and
growing my my Division I got pulled into
being the business development marketing
corporate Communications guy for a
billion dollar company and about seven
sub subordinate companies so
and I wasn't that person I didn't have
that training I wasn't that wasn't my
background but all of a sudden I was
trying to figure out how to pitch and
position Aviation companies and vehicle
companies and digital digital and
virtual training companies all kinds of
odd mixture of these different these
different
entities and initially to try to figure
out how to position them everything from
their brand awareness and and position
for success but but then I got sucked
into the operations of the company
companes so just just because I said yes
and went into that particular position I
ended up with about two or three years
of being the doctor going into a company
to look at their marketing piece and
some getting pulled into everything
marketing but distribution production
their Staffing levels do they have a
strategy do they have any kind of
planning at all and that actually became
my forte for quite a while it wasn't so
much what I started with I end up
segueing into this whole other piece so
that's just kind of how my life happens
uh the books same kind of thing I
decided I was going to write a science
fiction OB and I wrote it and uh I was
going to donate all the all the proceeds
to the seal veterans foundation and
then uh and then I ended up writing
three more science fiction books and
then five SEAL levels and I finished a a
10th novel about two months ago which
I'm shopping to agents and somewhere
about four years ago I started writing
business books basically because I
thought that would be interesting and
also would be helpful if I wanted to be
a consultant or a uh a business coach
executive coach Etc so yeah okay well it
sounds like you're kind of life is
stumbling you stumbling you into
positions that you're that you're fit
for in in some way tell me more about
this so at the beginning you had a
different intention and then you ended
up at this at the seals office um I'm
drawn to like use the word intuition in
here too I I want to explore more of
that like like how did you just follow
these little instances to listen and
start talking to certain
people at 17 years old well just about
18 when I showed up in California and I
didn't know anything about the SEAL
Teams back back in in in those days it
was totally classified there were no
movies there were no books nobody knew
anything about them so I really went in
there thinking they were going to figure
out how to fix my orders and send me to
a ship ship to be a radar guy
and and being you know basically about
18 years old I was very malleable so it
was very easy for it's very easy for
this gentleman um very nice guy he
didn't lie to me or anything but he he
just started asking me qu questions you
know and and uh and I answer him I
wasn't intimidated by him it just
sounded like a really fun thing to
do the way he laid it out and and he
actually you know he'd ask a question
like well did you ever play sports like
team sports yes what did you play there
like basketball football oh so you were
in football did did the coaches ever
yell at you when you weren't doing
performing correctly oh yeah that's how
the instructors are
here if you're not performing they're
trying to do the best thing they're help
to coach you and get better so they'll
yell at you and everything did they ever
punish you if you didn't do something
right oh yeah what were the what were
the punishments oh we have to run laps
or run up the stadium stairs or
something El or doing Wind Sprints oh
yeah yeah well that's the same kind of
thing here the punishment is really
reinforcement of of what they're trying
to teach you so it made it sound like I
was going to football camp right um and
then you know do you know to swim yeah I
swim competitively for eight years okay
so you're okay with the war oh yeah and
by the time he was done I thought well H
this seems like a perfect fit for me it
wasn't like I had this Intuition or I
didn't have a sense of the universe of
myself yet for sure but I think I I was
always had an awareness
of it wasn't it wasn't something
developed I had an awareness that
something seemed right like a
fit and having gone through 17 weeks of
air traffic control radar school and I
did that because my dad did that in the
Korean war in the
Navy I I'm not a tech guy although I
said on Tech boards and I'm not a uh you
know Electronics wiiz or anything but I
had to go through some Electronics
schools for that other that other uh
vocation but I knew that that didn't
seem as
fun as what this guy was
saying so it's kind of like signing up
for prison or war camp and not realizing
you think you're signing up for you know
soccer camp or something yeah but it did
change the course of my life in a really
big way yeah hats off to that
recruitment guy he he did his job really
well relating relating things that
you've experienced to uh potential
Futures you could see in the military um
okay so what
um so what so as you started working
with these other people um you were
saying that it sounds like you you
became the person who had all the
answers in some ways uh it sounds like
you just were an incredibly useful um
mind to have around and they were
floating you to where you were best used
what what was that all about what was
that like um did you intentionally come
in with like I'm gonna I'm going to have
a bird's eye view on this and have kind
of a a little bit to say about
everybody's individual or uh you know
jobs or or I guess I guess how did that
start let me let me talk about how that
ability kind of developed
so again part of kind of me you know my
pitch is to be creative you have to be
open-minded and you have to take risk
you have to kind of jump through that
hoop and see what's on the other side
and maybe it's not perfect and maybe
it's not even that great but you gain an
experience and Lou Pastor has this quote
Chance favors the prepared mind so it's
kind of like the thing that luck is when
you know opportunity meets hard work
kind of thing it's one of those kind of
deals but it's true so and I've told my
kids five kids all grown I taught them
the same thing there's no bad
job that that bad job that bad boss is
teaching you what not to do if you're
ever a boss it's teaching you how to
communicate better than that boss you're
G you have to suck every bit every ounce
of information intelligence about the
world life
workplace um working with your
co-workers maybe the business that you
happen to be in and then you're going to
move on because you know this is trauma
if you're a 16-year-old kid working in a
fast food place and then it's trauma
when you're 26 years old and it's your
first big job and it's trauma when
you're 44 and you just got laid off it
doesn't change because we're all human
being so I I learned
early uh as a kid I worked in lots of
different jobs I detassel corn I bailed
hay I worked in a warehouse I I uh for
one day I I manned the high pressure
hose and and a meat packing plant I was
too late to make that work so it was a
one day job but you you learn what
you're not good at too right so what you
end up with if you kind of see life that
way is you're kind of like this snowball
that's rolling down the hill picking up
everything that's on the ground the
snowball is getting bigger and more
powerful more
capable and you got all it reflects all
these different dimensions of of the
path you took and that makes you a
better Problem Solver because the the
open-minded approach and all this kind
of disparate goofy experience that isn't
aligned with a course or a
certification makes you very very
comfortable with the unknown and very
very comfortable with a scener where all
the assumptions are are not there laid
out perfectly in front of you and and
also operating with parts of those
assumptions being missing completely and
then you have to make make the decision
and take a leap of faith so if you have
a life like that which is kind of how I
started and the SEAL Teams kind of think
that way too the creativity is driven
that way open mind throw all the all the
whatever you did before the formulas and
everything get that out of your head
because every mission is a separate
problem set and you're going to get in
big trouble if you keep doing the same
football play over and over again even
if it's successful 10 times it's the
11th time it's going to blow up on you
to look at the problems in real time
assess the information in real time have
lots of contingency thoughts about what
happens if this doesn't go through or
that doesn't happen the weather's
different so that just reinforces what I
said through 20 years of that kind of
experience and training so it was easy
when I get in the business scenario I
outlined I didn't go in there thinking I
was going to be a business doctor you
know like Bar Rescue or something I
thought I was going to go in there look
at their website I was going to look at
their their marketing materials I was
going to see what are they doing for
promotion because that was my job at the
time and when you start talking to
business owners a smaller
companies they start confiding in you
about all the other elements of the
business because all it all ties right
if you don't have enough money to to run
an ad I better tell you why I don't have
enough money and that leads to I can't
sell anything or that lead my product
sucks or my service sucks or my
competition's kicking my butt next thing
you know you're sucked down the you know
business 101 rabbit
hole and you end up being a mentor and a
coach and a
consultant for the whole sweep of issues
all the categories because they're all
inter inter intermingled and they're all
related and I was actually solving
problems that were fixing things had
nothing to do with my primary purpose
and then people I worked for said
hey there's this other division that's
having problems and the biggest the big
billion dollar organization I want you
to go into that Division and I want you
to do an assessment so now all of a
sudden I'm I'm you know the business
doctor after two years but it was it was
a ramp up and a learning curve and it
was me learning to um not try to solve
everything right away but to listen and
hear what all the issues are because I
didn't know anything about Aviation not
not the the the art of buying planes or
fixing planes or moving planes across
the planet logistically I I didn't so I
couldn't give them an answer right off
the top of my head and be a know at all
I had to sit back and just
absorb so what so what do you think it
is if you had to pinpoint you know one
solid sentence or two of what it was
about you at that time like what what
did you have that it seemed that other
people's didn't other people did not uh
two things
uh uh the
open-mindedness because if you're open
if you're open-minded if you're
intellectually humble
it's amazing how much stuff you see it's
like the punch buggy thing all over
again you see things clearly you see
things even the people that you're
talking with don't see because they're
too close to it I'm on Boards of
technology companies because I have an
objective Viewpoint because I don't know
anything about robots or I don't know
anything about um high-speed uh drone
operations so I'm the one person in the
room that goes hey you know you got a
booger hanging out of your nose because
nobody's looking for that and and that's
valuable to a lot of people that they
have somebody that actually sees the
truth but to do that you have to have an
open mind the second thing is and this
happens with experience but also that
experience is formed by
being comfortable with taking a chance
with taking a risk because if you're so
risk adverse that you've mitigated all
opportunity away you're just a stick
stuck in the in the ground you're not
going anywhere the world's swirling past
everybody else is changing you think
you're safe because you think you really
your job is to mitigate and make
everything perfect well guess what your
product your service the way you run
your
company um it's all changed maybe
everybody in the neighborhood I've got a
friend that had a a training school and
it was fantastic because it catered to
kids after a
decade the revenue started going down
the head count started going down and he
wasn't sure why so he threw money into
advertising it turned out that where he
planted that school was perfect when he
when he put it there because the
demographic of the surrounding five to
to six M radius were parents with kids
in elementary school and then the kids
as they were shifting from elementary
school and middle school were flooding
his school but as they started to get to
high school right and the opposite was
happening and then if you took it like
another five years later he's surrounded
by empty nesters so the entire PO he
served the population but they had
evolved in left so he basically had to
shut the school down there and find
another location like that but it
happened so slowly
that he had no no conscious awareness
that was happening and so you know you
have to be able to take risks but you
also have to realize that you know
trying to trying to mitigate those risks
can actually uh cut off your
opportunities so those are two things
ability to uh have an open mind and uh
be intellectually humble coupled with
risk-taking yeah uh well it seems I mean
change is actually a pretty profound uh
change is even a continuous learning
process for me you know
uh a lot of a lot of like kind of my
world in this podcast has been started
from me trying to learn about myself and
uh I had some mental health things that
I was like man I got to get this stuff
figured out I've got to understand how
my own mind works um and that that's a
pretty profound fact is learning about
change you think you're going to get to
this arrival point of like I'll learn
about who I am and exactly why I am this
way and then it'll be that same way
until I'm you know 95 years old or
whatever but no it's a you know every
day you kind of have to accept who you
are that day um you have to accept in
every different transition and all of
your life when you start a new job when
you get into a new relationship any of
the stages of our life we kind of have
to take account uh who am I why am I
this way um and is it serving me going
forward because sometimes we're met
with we're understanding oursel we're
learning about ourselves um but we
but there's not necessarily an arrival
point I feel like I found that a lot
with myself there's not necessarily a
place where I get to where I Know Myself
100% I'm continuously learning about
myself um I wonder in your world Marty
where do
you what what do you see in other people
I mean you you've worked alongside a lot
of other people I mean I would love to
hear what your own experience about it
is too
um what happens when people start to try
to change what what are the frics that
come up when we when we want change um
what are the things that are difficult
for us to look at about who we are now
and that need changed uh what I guess uh
suppose what are some things that that
come up commonly in your world when it
comes to people trying to assert change
in their
life so there's there's a lot of brain
science now that has identified kind of
the the primordial original intent of
the brain to keep the human species
alive and there were two things one was
stability and
safety essentially full Mitigation Of
All risk you know you don't want to get
eaten by a saber 2 tiger and you want to
be able to find food all the time right
um and stay warm and all those kinds of
things the second thing was the
willingness to take risks and
explore because if you didn't do that in
the first case if you living in a valley
you'd eventually kill all the deer eat
all the fruit you know everything would
be you You' um Denude all Poss I food
sources and you starve to death and die
so you were had to be compelled and be
willing mentally to pick everything up
and take it into the unknown over the
hill and there's actually two switches
in the human brain that they located
that are functional parts of the human
brain which is part of what I write
about in and be different because that
allows you at any age unless you have a
a medical problem to be creative to take
chances to think big to have a a sense
of awe and wonder we just been taught
not to do that as adults that's not an
adult thing to do six-year-olds that's
okay but adults so that I think is a
premise to my answer to your question if
that's the way we're designed and if in
modern time say since the the late 1800s
mostly through public schooling we've
been conditioned to not take risks to to
hug safety and stability as as the be
end all you know the objective is
stability and and safety then what
happens is we are leaving ourselves open
to greater and greater and greater
emotional and psychological shock when
that reality turns out not to be
reality um Madam Cy who who discovered
radium has a quote that says the
universe abhor stasis in other words it
the universe hates stability and she's
saying because she was a scientist and
she realized everything she was looking
at was in a constant state of turmoil
and change and adaptation and evolution
or de Evolution or complete destruction
and just disappeared and and she goes
okay then what I'm going to stop trying
to contain this and control this and
codify this and catalog this because
that's not the way the world
works so if you think of what I just
said and and take your your question and
there's two people in a room and they
hear Hey the company is going to
um uh reduce the staff by
10% well usually when I tell my people
people I've been a CEO for now 15 years
everybody's about to communicate change
I said but what's the first thing
everybody's going to flash in their mind
the second you start to talk or and you
send out of
communication what's going to happen to
me so the best thing to do is to
frontload what's going to happen to you
you can start off with all kinds of wind
ups you know we've had a strategic
Retreat we did this and that and the
markets are changing and everything and
they're all going you know they're hyper
Ving because they're waiting for the
other shoe to drop right and the longer
they have to wait or the more vague your
communication the worse the outcome is
going to be as far as their mind's
concerned that's because any change even
before it's announced and maybe it
doesn't have anything to do with you any
change is perceived as a threat to their
stability their security their
stasis and you could take even down a
notch you can you can go to in
accountants and linear kind of trained
professionals are are are uh they do
this all the time you go up to an
account and you say hey I want you to be
part of a project team that's going to
be developed pricing for a bid we're
putting
in and if they've never done that before
they break out in sweats they go pale
and they stare at you because all they
see is failure because they haven't done
it before because what they are good at
is incremental repeating of of rules and
laws related to accounting and they went
to school for that and they were
attracted to that and what you just
basically said is I want you to go on
there and and show your ass and look
like fo and then you'll never be the
same again as far as we're concerned
because we'll remember how how bad you
were they think it's like you're going
to go in there and film them doing
karaokey or something that's the
psychological reaction so if you don't
hire
people with a with a more comfortable
mindset a willingness to work with other
people a willingness to roll with some
of the changes and you've had a really
interview for that kind of temperament
right if you don't do that what you have
is you've actually on purpose brought a
whole bunch of fragile mind mindsets
into a room and the only thing that that
hasn't happened yet is you haven't
announced your first change because then
once you do you're going to get what you
bought basically that that labor force
is going to react how each individual
reacts and the majority of them we're
going to get freaked
out now of course the opposite is true
if you bring in a bunch of people that
have been identified as
openminded uh comfortable with with some
change willing to work in Project teams
you know in uh multi-disciplinary groups
you know well then what's going to
happen is when you start talking about
change a lot of them are going to think
this is the opportunity and how can I
how can I how can I
help so that's a lot of prep you know
prep stuff environmental
stuff every it doesn't matter I can't
I've never been able to control every
single hire that's come into groups that
I've been put in charge of um and so you
have a mixed bag of all those all those
types of people um some of them step up
and go what can I do to help and some of
them were in the corner in the fetal
position and some people have already
dialed up you know a head hunter I need
another job I think I'm going to get
fired nobody's even announc anything
about firing and you get all the whole
Gambit and all you can do afterward is
try to manage everybody's psychological
reaction now the more you've been
through that the more you're kind of a
veteran Trooper of those kinds of
experiences you build up psychological
resilience to the moment and you still
May pick up the phone and dial Your Head
Hunter put them on St stand by because
you're not sure how this going to turn
out but you're not necessarily going to
go into panic mode yeah yeah I mean it
does make sense to have a plan in that
moment but uh you know I think we all
deal with potentially making things
worse when when they don't need to be uh
as a big of a deal as they as they
currently are um I wonder in in that
moment I think about the difference
between growth mindset and fixed mindset
a lot um I'm sure you have like some
great examples of those but uh
I I think that it's something that can
be learned like if if you think of
someone with a fixed mindset uh maybe
they kind of always been the certain way
I don't think that it's a death sentence
by any means I think that it's a it's an
active thing that we can invite
ourselves to do um and see where we're
being in a kind of a fixed mode of of
wanting comfort and safety but life or
whatever uh you know is is inviting us
to to have a growth mindset I think it's
something that that people can change
into um in those moments especially when
there's big changes happening at
corporations in uh places that you're
working
at what do you see because it seems like
you you have a pretty natural growth
mindset do you see other people with
fixed mindsets is there like some Lynch
pin that you can give them that opens
them up from a fixed set to a to a
growth mindset um I know my questions
are a bit rambly Marty but I hope
there's something that I can hand hand
you they're they're fine it's uh so
we're talking about Behavior
and and we're talking about modifying
the behavior for a particular purpose in
this case to be able to have more of an
open mind in a less reactive negative uh
response to some kind of an announcement
or change or something and a more
proactive and positive reaction right so
behaviors are all about training
training coaching
mentoring um I give you a perfect case
in point if uh everybody that's
listening to this unless this is
something you're practicing all the time
just stand on one foot in time how long
you can stand there before you lose your
balance now there are hundreds and
hundreds of little muscles and tendons
and ligaments that are involved in
stabilizing your leg including all the
bones of your
feet and your own mind the way it
perceives its its sense of
balance and you may find that you can't
keep it up you can't balance from more
than like five
seconds but is that your human your
human constraint does that mean all
humans can only balance on one foot for
five seconds or is that a
self-imposed uh constraint because
you've never
practiced I guarantee you if you
practice that a little bit every day
randomly you get a sense of what the
stability feels like when it's right and
you do that for 30 days and you probably
have know a two minute three minute
balance period which if you like numbers
the the percentage of improvement is you
know ex exponential right
it's the same thing with this kind of
human behavior it's practicing and
flexing and exercising all these other
types of
thoughts the the the open-mindedness is
a huge one because if you don't have
open mindness you won't even you won't
take a go on the train you won't listen
to anybody you know you just block it
out which again is kind of that stick in
the mud thing you're you're trying to
protect yourself from the risk of change
because in your mind all change is bad
all change leads to karaoke night
um and you have to have it as as a
cultural thing you have to have your
leaders thinking this way again you have
to this is a big part of of creating and
establishing and sustaining a culture
you have to do it at the hiring point
you can't just hire people that on the
resume can do exactly technically what
you're looking for and if you do it in a
panic because you're just trying to fill
fill a hole and you're bypassing all
these human
behavioral um uh what do you call it uh
when your compatibilities that you
really need in a culture then you're
just you're just bringing in a problem
you're bringing in a a psychological
grenade that's going to go off down the
road they not going to help in a group
project they're going to react violently
to every little piece of new information
so you can control a lot of this by how
you hire and then you you need to
improve upon it by evolving everybody
through this kind of mindful
behavioral excuse me
transformation from wherever they are to
a Comfort level with change and and and
there's ways to do that you can do it
through scenario Based training because
it's it's it's a game it's role playing
you get in a room and you say hey we
just lost our our number one supplier we
just lost our top salesperson we just
lost our biggest client or customer now
these are real things I have five kids
and some of them you know they're in
different businesses but this pops up
all the time hey we just lost our number
one client excuse me management team's
freaking out
right happens every day in business
happens it happens in small businesses
and large businesses and middle-sized
businesses somebody moves in across the
street and sets up a a pizza parlor and
you've got a pizza parlor but they've
got more more room and they've got more
money to throw at advertising and
they're putting everything at 25% off
and they're having a kids night or
Monday Night Football night you you're
caught behind the curve right that's the
way the world is that's that whole point
of the universe constantly changing
because you can't see everything but you
have to anticipate things are going to
change change and gaming this out
sitting in a room either doing it as a
as an exercise and brainstorming all the
possible things that could go wrong and
all the possible opportunities that
might be out there with your
team more you do that the more everybody
opens up and starts throwing something
into the
mix you can't do it once because
everybody that thinks you again it's
that karaoke night thing they don't want
to look stupid in public they'll just
sit there and clam up you'll get one or
two people that are just real
comfortable with flap on their lips and
everything but that's you know 2% of the
input potential so you have to cultivate
it you have to hire for it and you have
to maintain it by mentoring and doing
these practice
drills that way when the real thing
comes up and this how you do it in the
military you train harder least you know
seals for sure we train much much harder
um for combat than combat tends to
be right if we push ourselves harder and
we have more Things Fall Apart and radio
broken now how you going to communicate
or the helicopter never showed up to
pick you up now you have to walk you
know 15 miles through mountains or sand
whatever it that happens you all the
time and then you go to do the real
Mission and everything works and
helicopter shows up on time you go boom
boom boom and you're out if it's
anticlimactic yeah because you train to
a much worse set of pro um um
probabilities same you can do the same
thing in business you do same thing in
family family could even do this yeah I
I like that a lot I um I have
experienced a lot of my work is in in uh
I work in live event production and I
work with a lot of nonprofit
organizations that do um leadership
training so if you ever heard of uh like
HOSA or Deca or fbaa their like high
school leadership um organizations they
do a lot of mock trials and uh uh like
mock competitions and it was very
profound for me uh when I was young when
I was originally enrolled in Deca in one
of these organizations just having that
mock interview like the first time you
go in and have an interview just shaking
someone hand and introducing yourself
and being offered a problem or trying to
sell yourself and tell them why you know
you're worthwhile for them to hire you
at this job whatever um doing those mock
competitions a few times made me just so
cool and calm and collected when it
actually came time for real job
interviews it took away the anxiety and
so yeah it totally makes sense it's you
know you you run 15 miles with a 25
pound weight vest and then the next time
you run that exact same time without the
weight vest it feels pretty light and
big deal so yeah yeah that's that's
pretty profound um set setting people up
in these positions to where they're not
shocked when something that is an
evitably going to happen
happens um what what do you so I want to
talk about discipline how how do you see
discipline um I think that's probably an
Ever growing Factor uh I I liked uh I'm
sure you're familiar with like jao
willink uh he he has he has the popular
saying discipline equals Freedom um it's
it's a short simple thing but it's it's
a great one man it's I think that's
that's a pretty profound one so I I
guess I want to just open that door to
you Marty what do you think about when I
say discipline or or how do you think
about discipline that may be different
than the way other people
do well I think I think people over
complicate the discussion of
discipline the problem with discipline
is it's simple but it's
so candidly difficult that everybody
gets about halfway or 25% the way there
and realizes how hard it is and then
they stop so I'll give you an
example so with with the novel I just
finished in the three business books I
about 13 books and there are most of
them around 90 to 95,000 words so that's
13 times 95,000 words and if I tell
somebody that they're like how the hell
did you ever do that and I did it
basically about 200 to 300 words at a
time per day which sounds
not like a big
number but if I did it for seven days
and I did it for the next seven days and
I kept doing it until the book was
done then I've created a set of of
behaviors that become
habits and those habits repeated over
and over again to get the result that
you're trying to get which is in this
case is incremental momentum and
movement through a project that is the
definition of discipline from the
outside looking in everybody looking at
me says oh he so disciplined he gets up
at 5:00 in the morning he start trying
at 5:30 he always puts down at least 300
words and he's every single day bam he's
got a book bam he's got another book
he's so disciplined yeah okay fancy word
what it really means is doing whatever
it is has to be done over and over and
over and over again to get the result
that you're aiming for it may be nothing
more than then getting up and not
watching you know looking at your screen
on your phone
psychologically difficult people have a
really hard time with that right um I
I've turned my phone off or left my
phone places and walk around and and had
that same freak out everybody has I'm
missing all this I mean I know a CEO and
I got all this other stuff somebody's
calling me somebody just sent me an
email that I have to respond to and and
you experience the Freak Out you go this
is how bad my I am right now this is me
not having this thing in my hand right
but if I did that every day if I gave
myself three hours or you know four
hours of of the day that I'm awake where
I don't have this thing like in front of
my face in time the discipline of doing
it over and over and over again repeated
Behavior to achieve a positive
result reduces my anxiety eliminates my
anxiety and suddenly I realize I'm
coping without having to look at the
stupid phone which was the end State I
was aiming for you want to lose weight
you want to gain weight you want to you
know get bigger biceps you want to run
faster I mean there's physical limits to
physical goals and there are Maybe some
limits like I can't I can't dunk a
basketball I'm just too short to dunk a
basketball
um so you have to you know look at what
your objective is and before you start
watering down the objective set the
objective and give yourself a reasonable
amount of time to reach it and then
break it up into these little mini steps
with the seals that training technique
was called Baby Steps little tiny baby
steps to achieve each element or
increment of growth whether it's
knowledge growth or whether was skill
attainment
grow it's a you know eat an elepant one
bite at a time kind of thing and if we
do it that way and I don't know how you
were math I sucked at math but whenever
I had a math teacher that taught that
that way I was never left behind
whenever I went into a class like the
next year and the guy went and then the
next day he jumped to the next concept
if I hadn't picked up the day before
Concepts and been able to practice them
and figure them out I was a day behind
all a concept behind next thing you know
I'm halfway through the school year and
I'm way to Hell behind because that
teacher didn't care they didn't teach in
a way it was incremental and reinforcing
incremental and reinforcing that was a
discipline of learning and then evolving
into the next concept and then evolving
into the next concept they were just
throwing it out there and say execute so
you can't do that to yourself either you
can't set a goal and say I'm gonna make
I'm gonna achieve that goal in Leaps and
Bounds because that's not the way we
learn and that's not the way we change
right right yeah my uh uh chemistry was
was that for me it felt like I missed
one day or I was like nodding off one
day or something and like you said
before you know it halfway through the
through the semester I'm like I don't
know what's going on so I I feel I can't
catch up um but yeah I like that a lot I
uh it kind of reminds me of uh Dr Jordan
Peterson he talks about sometimes it
could be so daunting to look at the
giant staircase of like you know what
you want to accomplish or what you know
needs done to get to where you you know
point A to point B um but it can also be
easy to for some of us to kind of like
our own responses of doing
anything if we're too much staring at
the big the big staircase uh so he talks
about just hey you know if you can't you
can't write your novel this morning what
can you do you can go into your office
desk drawer and you could take a piece
of paper out and put it on the desk cool
maybe that's all you got today and then
tomorrow you grab a dang pen and you put
it on there maybe you write the first
sentence maybe you don't whatever um but
that was it was really helpful for me
man CU I
uh sometimes when you have all these
like creative amazing cool ideas you're
like that's awesome I want to attack
that I want to go on that I have this uh
excitement I have this momentum I have
this uh
motivation I want to attack this thing
that I know I'm going to be good at I
want to write this book whatever it is
um and then we realize you know we only
have 24 hours in a day and your
excitement doesn't match what you're
actually able to do in that day so
rather than just sitting down and
accomplishing nothing uh keeping that
momentum going I I I feel like it fits
into what you're talking about with the
um the the snowball analogy to where
like you run into different things and
they just become your snowball um I
think what happens often with a lot of
people is we we hit those things and
instead of keeping the momentum of our
snowball we like we got to stop and
check out what we just ran over and we
got to Define ourselves by
that pick it out of the snowball can't
see why we have any value we toss it out
to keep it clean and pure and safe and
yeah yeah yeah ex exactly okay so so
what separates what separates us from I
guess what keeps our momentum as the
snowball you know how do we notice when
we've been stopping to to take our
report card I say that often like you
know we want like how am I doing right
now who am I right now does this Define
me as as a whole and we give our letter
number grade and sometimes it's
defeating so how do we keep the momentum
of the Rolling snowball I suppose I'm an
advocate of
um of pull versus push
motivation and so push motivation is
you're either threaten yourself or
somebody else is threatening you with
some downside consequence if you
don't push forward and move forward and
keep doing everything to some volume of
completion and and then then if you
don't do that then you feel like you're
starting to fail it's like the chemistry
thing you're falling behind it's it's
all on you sure what are you doing this
for you just stop right but the pull
motivation
approach is you think long and hard
about the end State you think long and
hard about what you want to do what you
want to be how you want to look this
could be a personal thing it could be a
professional thing it could be if you if
you're you're in a company you could be
what do you want the company to look
like or your division or Department to
look like and then you have to solidify
that out there in the Horizon kind of
like a light you know and you're in the
desert or you're in the frozen tundra
and you see that light and what happens
is you you're compelled You're
motivated to move physically
psychologically emotionally and
Direction and of course it takes forever
for that light to look like it's gotten
any closer or any
bigger but you're being pulled towards
that light and that light is your
objective that is the cleanest purest
and I think the most powerful motivating
factor for
people the problem is there's so there's
so many programs and there's so many
books and there's so many you know
infomercials and all that and it's more
about pushing you it's it's pushing you
towards something and you haven't really
defined whether you want to go there yet
so if you don't want to go there
you're bound to fail because you're not
going to you're not going to incorporate
all the little micro Behavior changes
and the disciplines because you don't
you don't proceive the value yet or
there is no value for you so somebody
else can't set a goal for you like
you're going to be a lawyer so you're a
sophomore in high school I want you to
get good grades I'm to ground you
because I want you to be a lawyer you
know how that works you know and if you
look at the statistics of how many
people quit the first year law school
how many people that actually graduate
law school never actually go to take the
bar and go off to do some other thing in
in industry it's amazing if you saw it I
mean mind mind
numbing it's kind of sad because you're
thinking well if those people quit the
first year of law
school and they and they quit right
after they finished law school they
probably never really wanted to be
lawyers yeah so who decided that who who
made that their goal you know parents
family members peers so yeah push
doesn't work and and it's probably a
cliche in any profession if you get in
your third year of college and you
realize you never really wanted to go to
college it was your parents dream or you
never wanted to be the work in the in
the family business and take it over
that was your parents dream and you just
kind of stopped one day like four scump
ago I'm
done and you and he wasted all this time
sacrificing to achieve somebody else's
goals so figure out the goal and you
know if the goal is just next week
that's fine too you know I was talking
about before the baby steps you
basically set Big Goal way out there and
you say okay I think it's going to take
two years you know you don't go crazy if
it was gonna write a book you said it's
gonna take a year for me to finish the
first draft okay that's 12 months and
then you say all right so if I got 12
months then that's you know 52 weeks and
you start breaking it down into the time
chocks and you say so I basically have
to write 500 Words a week or something
you know and that means that I write 100
100 words a five day work week or you
know 67 words you know a day for seven
and then you're saying well I should do
that because you broke it down into the
increments and so your short range goal
is to get to the end of the month and
have achieved whatever that that count
is it'll feel like slow motion later but
in the beginning it feels like it's
taking forever because once you get used
to the Habit then you feel like the the
the increments are they too small and
the the short objectives are too short
and
you could actually do a lot more because
now you're getting into the pull part of
it you're getting sucked in you actually
start to get the confidence that and and
and the uh the courage I can actually do
this I'm in month two and I've written
this much or I've built this much or or
I've achieved this much my one-year goal
is achievable I can do this one step at
a time I can get that done but you have
to have that that big go to end you know
I can't remember what was uh the B ious
goal you know there was a book Business
book back in the 90s I think you have to
have a big audacious goal for the
organization that is worthy of sacrifice
and worthy of that discipline Behavior
change and repeated activity yeah yeah
um okay so so what do you think about uh
I suppose this might be aimed towards
more younger people but I think we all
probably have our own instances of it
throughout our life um you're just
talking about you know what we want to
do versus the voices of our parents the
voices of our influences um I think
sometime I mean I definitely find in in
this world of kind of the mental health
self-development self-help uh you know
um setting scenario uh nowadays kind of
like this whole self-help world I think
a lot of people come up against that is
they they get to a certain age and they
realize man I have a lot of momentum
towards things that I don't truly want
to do I I did not realize it until I was
28 but I was trying to please my mom
this whole time and now I got to reset
and go what do I what do I really want
um what what what do you think about or
or what has come across in your path
Marty um and even for you as
well those those times where we notice
oh geez I've been working towards
someone else's goal I I'm I need to
reset I need to take stock of what I
actually want to do um how do we kind of
find our own centers I guess how do we
take those moments settle reset and
align with our values not our
influences
so I I work with a lot of military
people that are transitioning out of
doing you know a 20 plus year career and
it's a culture shock to come out of
uniform because that's a that's a that's
a very fixed culture
and their expectations are are are
unrealistic
because they haven't been a civilian for
so long and they don't understand what
it's like to have a job and you you got
to do something pretty bad to get fired
in in the military because everybody's
trying to train you to be the best
person you can because you're part of a
team and we have to rely on you so
there'll be a lot of effort put into
correcting whatever the issues are to
get you at least to the medium standard
right that so unlike the regular
world if you were failing there may be
nobody that cares and nobody's going to
try to help you and you'll fail to the
point they'll just get ready and replace
you you're like you're like a um a bad
car part right so they're so they're
used to a loyalty system and they
they're also used to this audacious
endstate goal or objective so they train
hard and passionately and they're pulled
towards these things because they're
it's God in country it's it's you know
protect United States citizen that's all
okay now now they get out and they're
they're working as the the Regional
Manager of
Walmart little Goden country decisions
aren't related to the loss of life and
limb everything's
diminished the uh the pole part feels
like it's not there it's just a job it's
just a paycheck so you feel like you're
just stuck in paying the bills mode
where you used to have this life and
then the other part of it because you
know patriotism kind of waxes and waines
in US history but for the past 10 years
at least 12 years since
9/11 if you walked in in uniform in a in
a in a bar or any place in the United
States pretty much somebody would buy
you a beer say thank you for your
service wasn't always that way it wasn't
that way for the Vietnam guy wasn't that
way for the Korean War guys it was
definitely that way for the World War II
guys and and so guess what you don't get
all that big love hug kind of stuff
going on every day when he get out so
nobody really cares
it's I actually have a presentation that
I call thank you for your service now
what and it's to shock the these guys
and the fact that you know the the flag
and the medals and the box and all that
kind of
stuff it's kind of like the trophies
from high school football or swimming
whatever you know are you still walking
around saying I'm I'm the you know first
string left pulling card on the varsity
team no you're not you you aren't that
person and that is no long that's no
longer what defines you you know you
kind of put this in a place in your mind
this is a part of my life that I did
great things and I was successful and I
was respected and now I'm going to put
that word it is I use all the skills
that I attained and all the knowledge
and wisdom and all that but I can't go
from being a fighter pilot or squadron
commander and go right into being a
Fortune 50 corporate executive it's not
going to work that
way so when you look at
anybody and they have to transition
from who they are to some other kind of
person they have to first this is kind
of back to intellectual humility thing
they basically have to sit down and say
themselves I've got to shred myself of
all this negative and positive
baggage the positive baggage is
important too because if you think
you're the bomb diggity be all and all
then you're arrogant you're arrogant
about what you think you are and what
you're capable of doing and if you're
really arrogant you think you can do it
anywhere kind of back to the pilot
thinking they can be a Fortune 50
executive you're a you're an Olympic
boxer and you think you can go and be a
a swim coach or you can be you know the
head of a the head of a restaurant
they're totally different things it's
like I can speak Chinese I'm gonna go
ahead and speak farsy too just because I
can speak Chinese it's lunacy but
psychologically because because we want
to hug what we know makes us feel good
and feel stable and feel loved and and
and uh accepted and respected we tend to
think it's going to be a horizontal
transition to the next to the next big
thing it's not so what I usually explain
is you have to create this Apprentice
mindset and don't jump off of your day
job before you've done the research and
put in the work to figure out what you
want to do next because it takes time
and that's what I tell the military guys
too I said you got six months to a year
and you know you're have retiring it up
that's where you start going out out
there and whatever you think you want to
do learn everything you can about that
particular thing you'll find that you
don't really want to do it or you really
do want to do it then how do you want to
get involved in it so research that talk
to people people will help you all day
long you know you want to run a
restaurant the restaurant owners and
operators will tell you you know they
they'll help you out and but you have to
get into a mindset that I'm an
apprentice in this new thing I'm not the
master it's not a transition of I'm the
fighter pilot I'm the Navy steel and I'm
the Army commander and suddenly I'm in
charge of all restaurants because just
CA
and and and what I'll say to these guys
in the needle form I would say to
anybody if
you are honest and you think back to
whatever you're doing now that when did
you start and what was it like in your
first week or first month or first year
what didn't you know how many mistakes
did you
make think through that learning curve
that's the learning curve you have in
your next new
thing you're not going to start out
kicking ass and taking a going to start
out as an
apprentice now like I said in the
interview if you've been smart and
you've absorbed all these different
weird kind of things that you're
learning you're you're you're in the
trucking distribution business and you
want to go into the oil industry well
they're both linear movement of product
so there's a lot of things you learned
over here that are transferable and you
you dealt with people and you dealt with
technology and you dealt with uh time
and space issues and weit and load
issues we the same thing over here so
there are things that will transition
over but you don't know how to sell oil
or you don't know how to do all the
calculations so you're not an expert yet
so be an apprentice as much as you can
start studying before you go make your
leap in the military obviously there's a
date certain if you're not then it's the
same I tell my kids I tell everybody
give yourself six months to a year to go
from not knowing anything going through
The Apprentice mode to where you think
you've got a pretty good handle what you
need to do get the certifications you
need for this new
thing you know save the money you need
for for whatever you're going to need if
you have to do a startup or something
like that uh you can even go out and
work in some of these industries for
free on this you in your spare time and
and don't come in there and say I want
the corner office I want to observe
everything come in and say can I work on
the loading dock or can I work out in as
a bus boy and then can I go back and
work as the fry cook can I can I want to
see the whole operation because I want
to start my own restaurant
see and that that like said you're going
to get you're going to get there you're
going to you're going to evolve and all
the totality of all your other
experiences and knowledge and
capabilities will all come with you and
you'll be better than the average person
because you have all that it's kind like
a like a booster rocket yeah to help you
with your success yeah yeah and I
imagine it's you know after that first
few weeks of first few months of the
initial learning period where you're
just kind of figureing out what you
don't know after you really kind of get
a you know a what do they say like a a
hip hip in your get up or whatever the
saying is like you feel comfortable with
where you're at then your your access to
all your old info and all the other
skills that you have are able to like
have a place you you found
comfortability and you found kind of
your place in the hierarchy at your new
spot and then now all of your uh other
info can find its way in into that new
job um I was thinking about uh there's
this dude called Simon cynic he's a a
leadership motivational you've heard of
him yeah he's a he's great man I've
loved his books Leaders Eat Last is one
of my favorites but uh he talks about I
think it's in that book how he was a
speaker at this event um and he was kind
of the main speaker the main keynote one
year and they got him a car like picked
him up from the hotel they like brought
him his own uh coffee they like handed
it to him and he was a speaker and he's
like this important guy right this way
Mr Mr synic blah blah blah and then the
next year he wasn't the speaker at the
event but he was was just going to the
event and he talks about the difference
with his basically like name tag wasn't
there he wasn't the speaker nobody sent
a car to pick him up uh he asked about
coffee and they're like yeah there's
maybe like some old Dale coffee in the
back get it yourself type thing and so
he was just kind of talking about um I I
thought it was really profound how he
pointed out the differences between you
don't really get to take your name tag
with you in every room you walk into you
know you kind of got to start from right
you know and it's it's a profound lesson
it's probably a lot of humble pie that
people got to eat you know
throughout I had the same experience I
was in Atlanta last year and I did a
speech to uh a bu big business
organization 1,00 people and it was
actually it was supposed to be 1,600
seats but they had 200 standing in the
back and when I came out they had a guy
following me with a float camera thing
and and there was rock music and I came
out and there like four minutes of just
cheering just like you
know and and I don't normally do venues
that big so I really know what it's like
to be you know Axel Rose and come
out you know the lead lead guy in a in a
powerful rock band or something and I
stood there kind of like oh
and then and then I said okay I'll
I'll just go ahead and start and when I
got done the same thing and and they're
all reaching up to shake my hands so I'm
going down thing like I'm Elis shaking
hands and
everything and they did the same thing
they picked me up at the airport they El
me El me to the uh Atlanta Hilton I get
in there they' already prepped everybody
and there
were 2,000 people at this conference so
they all knew my face and everything
already this was the day before the
speech and people rang up to me um
security had to help me get into the
elevator because there was too many
people crowding around me and um I
actually then I called my wife and and I
told her about it and she joked she goes
who did they say you
were you know like they they said I was
you know something else you know and so
then you know I do the I have the
meeting with the executives all that
stuff and then I go and I do my speech
and I I'm done and the next morning I go
to the airport and my flights are all
screed up and I end up sitting in
Atlanta for 12 hours and I'm just some
dude on a plastic seat and it doesn't
matter who I am I'm not going to get
anything done you know the name tag is
right the name Tag's gone and my wife
goes well that's just the Universe
telling your ego to just you know shrink
back down to
yeah but that's that's a that's that's
reality
and again it's kind of back what I was
saying about if you're Navy sealer or
fighter pilot you know you got all chest
full of metals all this stuff it's
really it's really a big Fall From Grace
in a way it's it's the way it's the
reason why so many military people have
trouble getting out it's the reason why
professional athletes that have spend a
considerable amount of time as
professional athletes have a real
difficult time transitioning when they
get out I mean they're walking out there
and they're the center
of attention everybody in that town
knows they pay for the play for the
Pittsburgh Steelers every restaurant
they walk into people are like running
up I mean they're like rock stars right
and then a year after they get
out yeah it's a big mind it's a big mind
game yeah yeah I mean it's uh I think
that that moment is you know it's funny
I I come at it with this kind of silly
comical side just because I've
experienced my own versions of it you
know in uh in my different jobs and as
I'm getting um just involved in
different different environments uh you
know one one year I'm the important guy
and the next I'm you know nobody knows
I'm there whatever um I think that
the the the transition
is I don't know I I know I'm kind of
something I'm poking fun at it like it
is kind of silly but it's actually
deeply painful it's actually deeply um
to like come to a point in our lives you
know male or female where we have to
reinvent ourselves suddenly like like
the end of a chapter the end of a book
closes and it doesn't have to be
necessarily sorrowful or sad or a loss
necessarily then we have to reinvent
ourselves and we have to now insert
ourselves into this new hierarchy where
you know just a week before we we woke
up in the morning we knew where we sat
in the hierarchy we knew what we had to
do every day to prove that uh we knew
what it took to feel fulfilled when we
laid our head down and now we've got to
restart that um what uh
I don't know anybody going through those
transitions I I suppose what advice
would you have for them Marty what um
someone who and I guess I may be
speaking to the people who are having a
hard time with this they're having like
genuine sorrow they're they're having
trouble finding this new version of
themselves uh what do you think you
would you would talk to them
about well and this sounds kind of like
a you know Yoda or something
but and I mentioned intellectual
humility
so it's great you have a spike in in uh
in self-esteem in an event that you know
you're the center of the
universe um and there's something to
learn in that but mostly you experience
it especially it's a positive thing and
then when it's all gone even if it's
only going to be gone for a period but
maybe you never have that experience
again then you have to basically clear
your mind and be humble and
realize there's something to be learned
by I mean you can
learn you can learn when you're Ling on
the ground after you fell you you can
learn while you're up running and and
looking great you know you can learn in
almost any situation you just have to be
aware you have to be aware that and back
to what I I told my kids when they were
first going into jobs and everything
that's happening to you good or bad is a
learning experience every it's a it's
the school of life so if you aren't sure
and something comes up I'll I'll pick up
the phone and call me but I guarantee
I'll squeeze some value out of it that
will help you down the road and you
won't remember it but when you're 20 or
when you're 30 you're going to say
someday you know what that thing that
yeah guess what it's it's happening here
but it's not a shock to him because it's
part of life it's part of human nature
it's part of whatever so
if you take what life gives you and you
accept it and then learn from it which
sounds TR but I mean really accept it
and really learn from it and not not go
through the emotional of I'll never be
that big a deal again or wow I am the
big deal and I'm going to be that that
way every day you know that that's not
reality deal with your the reality in
the moment and learn from it and
circumstances in the context of the
moment and like that big that big speech
I mentioned or having a chest full of
metals after
20 years um thank you for your service
good job now what's
next what do you got for me what we
gonna do next don't rest on your laurels
you can appreciate them but don't don't
ride them into the future thinking that
that's going to give you some kind of a
a pass on reality it doesn't the doesn't
care yeah that's uh that's pretty
powerful stuff I mean that's uh again
not not easy but it's it's valuable it's
it's useful I uh I work in a lot of
Realms of uh I like a lot of Buddhism
stuff a lot of stoicism type stuff um
and acceptance is something I'm always
learning it's it's not easy but it's
it's a constant reminder it's a constant
daily thing of acceptance cool yes I did
serve that yes I did accomplish those
things but now it's time for a new
chapter let's accept that let's not
dwell on where I was and how upset I am
that I'm not there anymore you know the
sun still came out today and what what
can I do today so um yeah it's pretty
powerful stuff man I wanted to ask you
um uh there was a couple things that you
said in in in your book that just kind
of made me want to ask you about uh just
freedom in general freedom of speech
freedom of thought um you kind of had
like a a mention uh about cancel culture
in there I think that's kind of a fun a
fun thing to bring in um I I I suppose
just broadly man what do you think about
why is freedom important what does
freedom mean to you um and I'm
definitely thinking freedom of thought
too not just like the law freedom I
think
you know my ability to to think of
whatever it is that I'm thinking of is
is is involved in that so I suppose just
big old Circle that for you Freedom
question mark Marty what what comes to
mind
man so there's there's a lot written on
on
this and the power of your mind and the
power of being able to think freely
within your mind and
range far and wide without
physically moving so um there's lots
written about the um the pilots that
were kept in Hano Hilton during Vietnam
for many many many years and and how
they stayed alive but really how they
stayed sane how they used their minds to
basically live a life that was worth
living and to
contemplate all kinds of things and to
make it day day to day Victor Frankle in
his book on man search for meaning about
his time in the Nazi and Turman camps um
same thing and it points to those that
were able to be free
in their mind as opposed to those people
that um took the consequences and
interacted only with the consequences
and got so depressed that they ended up
basically dying of depression you know
they basically died because they
couldn't handle the circumstances where
the people that
survived understood the
circumstances and then said okay the
rules were different I'm no longer a
banker I'm no longer this no longer that
I need to learn this universe I need to
learn these rules in this place and then
I be have to become a master of these
rules I have to St stay alive and the
best way to motivate yourself in those
situations is to help other people
around you because you stop thinking
about yourself all the time so those are
mind games but they're important mind
games and it's a freedom of the mind so
if you're sitting in a Cell in Hanoi or
you're sitting in a in a Cell in uh in
Nazi
Germany if your brain's not defeated if
your mind is not defeated then you're
not defeated so those are extremes right
and and as extremes they're they're
great because they show that if you're
physically constrained and and you think
you're constrained in other ways
financially uh uh geographically
whatever you think your constraints are
your mind isn't so you can conceive of
almost anything and work it through and
storyboard it in your mind and play it
different five different ways color it
any color you want to color it stretch
it out shrink it down compress it add
players take players out you can do this
all day long as long as you realize that
your mind has the freedom and the
capacity to do that and that that is
actually a really positive thing and and
humans are unique of all species on this
planet to be able to do that and that's
imagination that's creativity that's
using a sense of wonder and um and
taking a not knowing and trying to
convert it into someone understanding
and knowing
all all without getting out of a chair
so if you can do all that in your
mind then you could probably handle
almost anything that comes at you as
long as you have the freedom of
intellect to to deal with it
intellectually I don't mean like
academically inally I mean like
applying your brain and the mechanics of
your
brain what what I mentioned in the book
is that we''ve all been told we can't do
that we've been told not to do that
there's very little reward after you're
about six or seven years old to think
freely to dream to wonder to awe have a
sense of awe if you raise your hand when
you're 14 years old and say I think I
want to be an
astronaut the social
reaction is going to be almost immediate
and you're GNA say oh then you go home
and you say I want to be an
ason and your parents want you to be a
lawyer so immediately it's going to be
they're going to pound that astronaut
thought out of you and and get back on
track this is what you're this the only
thing you're supposed to think about so
your intellectual Freedom starts to get
compromised and you start thinking that
that's the only way you're supposed to
think like an
adult and like a sober adult meaning
you're not supposed to think paying
Outside the Lines the path has been set
go to school get good grades get good
grades to
get into another school get good grades
to get a good good job get a good job
stay there keep your nose clean have
tenure you'll start advancing up the
ladder you know and then you retire
somay it's that linear American Dream
thing but when you look at the people
that everybody talks about when they
talk about the American dream it's not
those people it's the Risk Takers it's
the people that take chances and think
think big and act big and fail and get
bankruptcies and start all over again
and and usually they come from other
countries because they don't know that
there's a linear plan so they just go
for it right because their mind says I
have nothing to
lose
and and I don't have a preset battle
plan my parents didn't say to do it a
certain way so soci didn't say to do a
certain way so and it takes you're when
you're B your your time time you're an
adult and you're sitting there there and
you're your first or second job and
you're confer table and somebody has a
problem and you raise your hand every
looks at you and you don't have the
right title you don't have enough time
at the company and everybody just looks
at you like you have three
heads and they don't call on you because
you haven't paid your dues yet that
suppresses and compresses your impulse
to think think big or to be creative or
to even participate in solving these are
not mechanical brain problems these are
not human constraints these are
constraints of society and all the
constructs that Society has put around
us and you know I make a point in the
book that's why I think you know the
cancer culture thing uh and it may may
be over by now but that is a social
reaction but really looks like the same
thing that I just said it's don't think
a certain way don't don't talk a certain
way you know and there was a time where
you don't dress a certain way when I was
you know like in the late 60s 7s you
know if you wore jeans to school you're
in trouble MH you had to wear you had to
wear you know chinos or something so you
um these things were these things were
imposed on you to stop you from
expressing yourself but they weren't
about breaking
laws that that the freedom we're talking
about isn't about you want to be able to
do whatever you want to do however you
want to do it physically and impact
other people this is about intellectual
freedom and the freedom of the so yes
I'm I'm a big advocate of it I I I think
it's it's something that's it can be
relearned than adults I think it's
[Music]
um it's back other things we were
talking about it takes a little bit of
practice to build the Habit to not react
immediately by constraining and
containing your thoughts and conforming
but to instead you know take a shot put
the hand up and that they don't call on
you go ahead and say it out loud anyway
um and if you're an organization where
they just keep stomping on you and
everything anything find someplace else
to work yeah yeah I love that what a
great answer man I I think about that a
lot because I uh I spend a lot of world
in a lot of time in the world of
creativity I do a lot of uh some some
sort of musician I do a lot of artist
Artistry stuff writing poetry whatever
and so I'm I'm often I spent a lot of
time contemplating what it really means
to have free thought and and how amazing
it is that we that we have it like how
cool it is that we're able that I'm able
to sit in my apartment and think about
and talk about the things that I'm able
to talk about the fact that I'm able to
record this conversation and I can kind
of collectively say whatever I want I
mean that's that's pretty cool um well
so uh Marty we're getting up here in
time um I I would love to just kind of
round us back on uh your your latest
book um I found that one thing that I
really loved about it was I think just
as a quick thought my brain doesn't
accompany military with creativity or
like being rebellious and joining the
military um but I feel like you you laid
it out in in such a nice way it kind of
changed my perspective a little bit um
and your book was very enticing so I
would love to just kind of uh at the end
here just for anybody who's listening
who's kind of thinking about checking
out your book who's your book for um
what are kind of some mind mindsets that
you would like to uh who would you like
to attract to your book I I
suppose well you know I the first two
books were focused more on
organizational issues like the being
able was about leadership and crisis and
be uh be Visionary was about strategic
thought and development of strategic
thought into an actual plan of action um
the be different especially the subtitle
of how Navy Seals and entrepreneurs Bend
break or ignore the rules to get results
it's kind of what we've been talking
about for the last 10 minutes it's the I
I saw that you know the first two books
are useful to Business Leaders doesn't
have to be a profit business leader it
can be an organizational
leader but what's was missing was and
I've in in working with these technology
firms there's a lot of
creativity there's a lot of of rapid
prototyping Innovation a lot of
experimentation which means there's a
lot of failure and it's it's a mindset
related to Leading Edge technology but
they human beings are exercising these
things and I'm watching why are we doing
that in the clothing business where
doing that in the car business why are
we doing that in in you know the medical
business that I'm in why are we just
kind of stuck in the status quo it's
because we're missing this creative
engine this willingness or the Comfort
to exercise and practice creative
thinking and then that's where I started
getting into the Conformity thing I
found some research uh that was done
proving exactly the same thing they
tested kids from like six years old to
40 and uh their creativity score went
from like the the high 90th percentile
down to like 5% and it was almost a 45
degree Decline and then I thought okay
so it's going to be based on age or
something they said no it's based on the
amount of exposure to institutional
learning and institutional management
and it was exactly and I had already
written the book first draft when I read
the research and it basically conf
confirmed the first couple of chapters U
of my book focus on which is this
obedience the blind obedience formity
and compliance intellectual compliance
and they say that's the problem you know
they're not allowed to think think
anymore they're not allowed to dream
they're not allowed to do all these
things so that was cool and I thought
all right so what really what the book
is going to be about is to tell people
it's
okay to paint outside the lines it's
okay to think differently but to think
differently you have to basically
convert yourself and be different
because you're going to have to change
your whole mindset about life and work
and and yeah there's going to be it's a
little bit about your mindset about risk
because being creative and Innovative is
a big
risk-taking uh Endeavor people are going
to not like what you say there's going
to be a social social cost to it small
social like in an organization or big
social
sometimes but if you start looking back
at all the people that we point to and
say wow they're so creative and so
Innovative they were so brilliant
Einstein was was like 21 years old he
came up with the special theory of
relativity Alexander conqu conquered
most of the new Known World before he
was 30 um Tesla I mean almost anybody
you point to we see pictures of these
guys especially in the last hundred
years as old men because that's when
when cameras in photography and and film
you know like Ford those guys look like
the little men but they all they all
invented and created what they created
when they were in their 20s and the
reason they're they're they're such
icons is because they did what other
people weren't doing wouldn't do you
know so we've been talking about that
theme through the whole the whole
conversation is you know set your goals
create an incremental plan to achieve
those goals focus on the goals let the
goal pull you there and the book
basically tells you to do that but also
to allow yourself and to train and
prepare yourself to think and and and
then act and be different as a
result yeah what a way to wrap it up man
that was great I I love that had this my
like 10th 11th and 12th grade in high
school my uh drama or theater teacher he
would always say darare to be different
he was kind of the first one to to
impose that on us and uh it it stuck
with me I feel like I use it as this
little um this little uh bit of
encouragement in moments where I'm like
what am I doing I'm I'm being weird
right now but it felt like the right
thing to be done for me it felt like
something that I could do um and I
looked around clearly other people are
not thinking the same thing as me but it
feels like like it's the right thing to
do so I'm going to act on it and and I I
never regretted acting on on on things
like that so um wow Marty uh man I want
to thank you for your time uh I really
appreciate this I I I want to thank you
for um the most recent book I think
we're GNA have to crack into your other
ones too as well I'm I'm kind of curious
to read your so you have so you have
non-fiction books and fiction books how
many non-fiction do you have three three
and then you have nine other ones I have
nine published novels and then the 10th
one that I'm I'm shopping to agents
right now okay anybody who's kind of
interested in checking out your novels
what do you think is like the first one
you'd probably send them
to ah well if they like science fiction
it's called um a time for Glory and
thanks go to Martyr strong.com the two
uh fiction series The Books are at the
bottom of the home of the landing page
and also the the the coverage of the
three business books so if you click on
that it'll take you right to the
information or for a point of sale um
the first sealed book in the series is
called uh Death Before Dawn and bul
books takes a a kind of naive
young person and evolves them through
the series until they're a much more
evolved and and more powerful
personality not necessarily perfect or
anything but but uh you get to track how
they how they evolve over
time yeah cool it sounds like it hits on
the old hero's journey I'm always a big
fan of that um cool man well well thank
you thank you so much I will definitely
include all of that info in the so we'll
be able to click on your link and
everything below so listeners check that
out um and then just the last thing I'm
just kind of curious what do we have
coming from you in the future it sounds
like you're definitely someone who uh
you know chips away at it day by day but
uh do you have anything on the horizon
we could be looking out
for I actually don't I I think I'm gonna
start writing some articles just to keep
you know warmed up with writing the um
when you write a book you know you're
kind of in it deep and then then you
finish it and then you have to start I
use beta read readers so people that are
interested in sci-fi or people are
interested in the whatever the the genre
topic of the book is to read chapter by
chapter give me feedback I do the same
thing with the business books I got a
group of CEOs and people that have a lot
of business experience who give me
feedback chapter by chapter so I I do a
stream of Consciousness writing in the
first draft and then I go back and I
look at all the input for by chapter of
three to four beta readers and uh
sometimes like it's mechanically good
you know the character had was
left-handed in the second chapter now
they're right-handed in chapter 15 you
know little weird things like that
sometimes it's my voice like in the
business books I shifted from my books
are very uh conversational people said
it's like a a mentoring program and I'm
definitely I'm audible when you listen
to it um but if I start to get too Tech
Technical and it starts to on to
textbook I get called on by those guys
and I've had to rewr rewrite an entire
chapter because I shifted into technical
writing mode and that's more like here's
the information instead of kind of
weaving back and forth like a a
Storyteller teacher you know guide which
is the way the books are written so um
but when you're done with the this
inputting all that information that's
your second draft and then I I get it
edited by a freelance editor and that's
the third draft and so you're pretty
much you don't even remember why you
wrote the book by that time and you're
kind of like numb and then if you
publish the the book like my my business
books for sure the publisher wants to
wait eight months when it's ready so it
can get on all the worldwide
Distribution Systems and all that and so
it just sits there in pre-sale for eight
months and then when it actually comes
out it's been 18 months since I started
to write it yeah so what but I've had to
do the business books no kidding as I
was on a lot of interviews for the first
book be nimble and uh they were asking
me questions because I read the book and
some of them had the book all you know
marked up and everything and I'm like i'
already I just finished being Visionary
I'm like what the hell did I saying be
be nimble like I wrote that sound two
and a half years ago or you know we like
well that sounds pretty smart but you
know but then when comment why did you
say that so iidea back I went back and I
got the audible versions I started
listening to in my truck I did that and
I did it I did it with be Visionary and
I just pulled down be different for the
same reason because you know you move on
you evolve you know and so I don't
really have a project because I'm just
kind of numb from the finishing this
10th novel and in the search for the
Aging right yeah I'm I'm sure I'm sure
there's novels being worked on every day
in some subtle way though within your
mind man I'm sure I'm sure that's going
on well well well cool man uh yeah
that's really cool I'm looking forward
to to hearing whatever it is that you do
uh come across next um I'll be sure to
follow you on on social medias and all
those sorts of things um you and I will
be in touch Marty as far as listeners um
I hope you're having a good day I hope
you're drinking some water I hope you're
stretching a little bit I hope you're
challenging the way that you've been
thinking um and uh yeah click down below
if you want to check out more Marty
stuff I recommend his newest book I like
it so far and uh yeah I thank everybody
for your time Marty thanks so much again
man uh we we we will be in touch and
I'll let you know when this thing's
releasing and all that so thank thanks
again I really appreciate your time
thank you have a great day cheers man
Merry Christmas to you too as well same
to you take care bye
[Music]
everybody no knowledge is
power reality
is junkyard love podcast